Guide to the Hugh R. Mouat Papers, 1941-1980
Mouat, Hugh R. papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Hugh R. Mouat Papers, 1941-1980
6607
Mouat, Hugh R.
0.7 cubic ft.
Newsletters, certificates, paintings, engravings and photographs.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Newsletters and certificates pertaining to otterhounds and the Otterhound Club of america. Also includes engravings, an oil painting, and photographs of otterhounds collected by Hugh R. Mouat.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Known as "Mr. Otterhound," Dr. Hugh R. Mouat wanted to preserve the otterhound bred of dogs in the United States, which he worried were becoming extinct.
He attended Cornell University's N.Y.S. Veterinary College from 1925-29, and received a D.V.M. He eventually settled in Amsterdam, NY, where he ran Adruicha Kennels. In 1948, he donated the body of one of his otterhounds named "Bessie Blue" to the Smithsonian Institute "for taxidermy and for display in the mammal section." In 1960, he formed the Otterhound Club of America, a branch of the American Kennel Assocation. In 1966, with the help of W.J. Doods, D.V.M., Dr. Mouat created a program of free blood testing for otterhounds who are often born with hemophilia.
Many of Dr. Mouat's otterhounds competed and won certificates and trophies. Some of his writings include "Otterhound: A Complete and Reliable Handbook," "Otterhound Champions, 1952-1994," and "How to Raise and Train an Otterhound," as well as numerous articles.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection contains, miscellaneous newsletters, writings, certificates and photographs. These materials pertain to Dr. Hugh R. Mouat and a breed of dogs known as otterhounds. Dr. Hugh Mouat, D.V.M. Cornell class of 1929, was known as "Mr. Otterhound." Throughout his lifetime, he sought to preserve the rather small breed of otterhounds, in America. In 1960, he formed the Otterhound Club of America and was known for helping to create a series of blood tests for otterhounds, who often are hemophiliacs. This collection includes a number of certificates that were won by Dr. Mouat's otterhounds, Otterhound Club newsletters, miscellaneous articles written by Dr. Mouat, and artwork featuring otterhounds.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Mouat, Hugh R.
Subjects:
Otter hounds.
Form and Genre Terms:
photographs.; oil paintings; engraving (printing process)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
For more information on Otterhounds please visit http://clubs.akc.org/ohca/
CONTAINER LIST
- Otterhound Club of America newsletters, 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous articles including one from the American Kennel Club Gazette (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Hello.. .I am an Otterhound" pamphlets by Hugh R. Mouat (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Kennel Club Championship Certificates, 1941-69 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Blood test laboratory certificates for otterhounds, 1968-74 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Certificates from the Otterhound Club of America fun match, May 30, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- War Department Certificate (Box 1, Folder 7)
- List Gifts of Dr. Hugh R. Mouat to the Flower Library, May 23, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Otterhound photos (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Otterhound engravings (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Oversized painting, engraving and photograph (Box 2)